<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.000000">
<title confidence="0.562208">
AN ERS MODEL FOR TENSE AND ASPECT INFROMATION
IN CHINESE SENTENCES
</title>
<author confidence="0.955225">
Hsi—Jian Lee* and Ren—Rong Hsu
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.971467666666667">
Department of Computer Science and Information Engineering
National Chiao Tung University
Hsinchu, Taiwan, 30050
</affiliation>
<author confidence="0.578182">
R. O. C.
</author>
<bodyText confidence="0.975376428571429">
ABSTRACT In this paper, we address a ERS model of time and aspect in Chi-
nese sentences. We first discuss the possible tense forms in simple sentences
when translating from Chinese into English. Next, we also address the possible
combinations of the tense forms of complex sentences joined by linking ele-
ments and some complex sentences containing one subclause. Finally, we pro-
vide some conventional rules in English to modify the tense forms before gen-
erating the output English sentences.
</bodyText>
<note confidence="0.693387">
*To whom all correspondences should be sent.
</note>
<page confidence="0.98133">
213
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.975838" genericHeader="abstract">
1. INTRODUCTION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999628">
Both tense and aspect in sentences play important roles in transmitting temporal and
situational information between human beings. For a machine translation system, the analysis
of tense and aspect has great influence on the quality of the output sentence. Lacking the
analysis of tense and aspect may result in syntactic or semantic errors. Take the following Chi-
nese sentence as an example.
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.955446">
(1) ta1 zuo2-tian1 mai3 1e5 yi4 ben3 shu1
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.994319111111111">
The corresponding sentence in English should be
(1a) He bought a book yesterday.
The translation such as
(lb) He buys a book yesterday.
would be illegal. Without the analysis of tense and aspect, a human being can hardly translate
sentences correctly, neither can the machine.
The tense can be viewed as determined by the relationship between the time of the
action or the state denoted by the verb and the time of speech. Thus, the tense information
involves at least three components: The event time, the speech time and the degree of under-
standing of the subject between the hearer and the speaker. On the other hand, aspect does
not refer to the time relation between the event time and speech time, but to how the situation
itself being viewed from its internal structure[1]. All the information of tense and aspect re-
flecting in the verb sequence and tense form will be defined in the following section.
In order to transfer tense and aspect information of Chinese sentences into those of
English sentences, we have to find the relationships between these two languages, which has
been done in [2] and will be summarized in Section 2. In this paper, we will address the prob-
lem about the possible tense forms in a sentence. Still, the sentences we will analyze are con-
fined to simple declarative sentences, which contain only one predicate. We will also analyze
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.987477">
214
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.518828">
some more complex sentences joined by linking elements such as &amp;quot;de5 shi2-hou4&amp;quot;(when),
&amp;quot;yi3-hou4&amp;quot;(after), &amp;quot;yi3-qian2&amp;quot;(before) and some sentences containing one subclause. We
also provide some conventional rules to modify the tense forms before generating English
sentences.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996718" genericHeader="method">
2. FORMALISM OF TIME AND ASPECT
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.998478666666667">
In an English sentence, the verb sequence is one of the most important constituents,
which are generally affected by the tense and aspect. Winograd [3] defined the verb sequence
as a sequence of verbs and auxiliaries following a fixed order, as ifiustrated below:
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.625628">
(Modal) (Have) (Bel) (Be2) Main Verb
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.9043135625">
where Modal has either the tense meaning or modal meaning; Have represents the auxiliary
has (or have or had); Bel represents the verb be; Be2 denotes the clause being passive if pres-
ent and Main verb is self-explained. Each combination of Modal, Have, Bel, Be2 and Main
verb is also called a tense form. For example, the sentence
(2) He has finished his job.
Model Have Bel Be2 Main verb
has the option Have, but has no other options (Modal, Bel, Be2). Indeed, it has the tense form
of &amp;quot;present-perfect&amp;quot;.
Many linguists take only present and past as tense, future is considered as the modal.
This kind of classification is not intuitive since human beings always partition the time axis
into three parts: past time, present time and future time. Winograd [3] proposed that the first
element of the tense sequence is the tense of the first element in the verb sequence unless
it is a modal. The rest, correspond to the entire auxiliary sequence, excluding the main verb,
are assigned tense features according to the following mapping:
element in a verb sequence tense feature
Modal Future if the word is shall or will
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989137">
215
</page>
<figure confidence="0.8208996">
Modal otherwise
Have Past
Bel Present
Consider the following sentence,
(3) By the time he comes home, I will have finished my job.
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.982755">
The tense sequence for the clause &amp;quot;I will have finished my job.&amp;quot; is (Future, Past) since &amp;quot;will&amp;quot;
gives the feature Future and &amp;quot;have&amp;quot; gives the feature Past. Now, we summarize the tense se-
quences (excluding the feature Modal) of possible verb sequences in Table 1.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.716581">
Table 1
Tense sequences for the sequences
</tableCaption>
<table confidence="0.978599">
tense sequence examples
Pres (4) I read every day.
Pres Pres (5) I am reading now.
Pres Past (6) I have lived here for six years.
Pres Past Pres (7) It has been raining on and off since this morning.
Past (8) I wrote a letter yesterday.
Past Pres (9) I was reading when he came in.
Past Past (10) When he came in, I had finished my job.
Past Past Pres (11) I had been reading a novel till he came to see me.
Past Fut (12) She was going to give me her address.
Past Fut Past (13) He once said he was going to have fixed all radios in
</table>
<bodyText confidence="0.643517166666667">
town by the time he was forty.
Fut (14) I will go to Taipei tomorrow.
Fut Pres (15) I will be reading when you come back.
Fut Past (16) When you come back, I will have finished my job.
Fut Past Pres (17) I will have been learning English for five years by
next month.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.991314">
216
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.94568432">
A problem in the above formalism appears when the sentence involves the progressive
or perfective aspect. For example, it gives sentences (8) and (9) the tense features (Past) and
(Past, Pres) respectively to capture their differences by time. However, both events in these
two sentences occurred during the past time. What makes them different is not the time but
the aspect. Thus we would like to give both sentences (8) and (9) the same time denotation
and use other feature to capture their difference.
As mentioned above, the tense sequence is got by tracing the elements in the verb se-
quence in order. Unfortunately we can not apply it in Chinese sentences since there is no tense
marker in Chinese. Thus, we have to use other information in a sentence. Here, the informa-
tion we use is called temporal information. To represent this information, we partition the time
axis into three parts which are past time, present time and future time. We can also divide each
partition recursively. Therefore, the temporal information can be used to denote the relative
relationship in the time axis. The representation for this relative time is called &amp;quot;time marker&amp;quot;.
There are two aspects in English - perfective and progressive. Since these two aspects
greatly influence on the tense form of English sentences, we choose aspect as the other attrib-
ute to represent the information for the tense form. Thus perfective or progressive are the
two aspect marker.
Based on the time and aspect markers mentioned above, we distinguish the tense form
of English by the values present, past, future, perfective and progressive. The tense forms of En-
glish sentences and their attribute values are listed in Table 2. Taken the tense form &amp;quot;past-per-
fect&amp;quot; in item 7 as an example, its time marker past-past denotes the event specified by the
verb sequence occurred in the past, with respect to the past reference time. Consider the fol-
lowing sentence
(18) ta1 hui2-jia1 de5 shi2hou4, Zhang1san1 yi3jing1 zuo4-wan2 ta1 de5 gong1zuo4 1e5
( When he came home, Zhangsan had finished his job. )
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.976402">
217
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.642458666666667">
The pair of time and aspect markers for the verbs &amp;quot;hui2-jial&amp;quot; (go home) and
&amp;quot;zuo4-wan2&amp;quot; (finish) should be {past - } and {past-past perfective } respectively. The meth-
od to determine these markers has been discussed in [2].
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.994164">
Table 2
Table of Tense Forms
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.963638923076923">
tense form
1. present
2. present-progressive.
3. present-perfect
4. present-perfect-progressive
5. past
6. past-progressive
7. past-perfect
8. past-perfect-progressive
9. past-future
10. past-future-perfect
11. future
12. future-progressive
13. future-perfect
time marker
present
past
past
past
past-past
past-past
past-future-past
future
future-past
aspect marker
present
progressive
perfective
perfective-progressive
past
progressive
perfective
perfective-progressive
past-future
perfective
future
progressive
perfective
14. future- erfect-L. ro ressive future-past -essive
</figure>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.887404" genericHeader="method">
3. POSSIBLE TENSE FORMS IN SENTENCES
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999851428571429">
We have provided a formalism of time and aspect to determine the tense form of
the sentence. That is, if we can find the time and aspect markers of a verb, we can find the
tense form through Table 2[2]. However, there is another approach to determine the tense
form of an English sentence which will be translated from the Chinese sentence. This ap-
proach is based on the relations among speech time (S), reference time (R) and event time
(E) proposed by Han Reichenbach in 1947 [4]. In this section, we will discuss the possible
tense form in simple sentences and those in sentences containing two events.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.957533">
218
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.970732">
3.1 Formalism of E, R, S and Aspect
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.929042">
To analyze the tense system of English, Han Reichenbach found that the analysis based
on the absolute event time or the relative time relation between event and speech is not
enough. Thus, he proposed the speech time, reference time and event time to account for
the underlying structure of the English tense system. The speech time and event time are self-
evident, while the reference time is the &amp;quot;temporal perspective- from which the described
event is viewed[5]. There are six relations among E, R and S in simple sentences, which corre-
spond to different tense forms, as Table 3 shows.
Table 3
The Mapping Between (E, R, S) and The Tense Form
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.990081375">
FRI
relation of E,R,S tense form
E = R = S present
E &lt; R = S present-perfect
E R &lt; S past
E &lt; R &lt; S past-perfect
S&lt; E = R future
S&lt; E &lt; R future-perfect
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.986662666666667">
From this table, we find that the relationships among E, R, S are not enough to represent
all various tense forms in English. Take the following sentences (19)-(20) as examples. The
relations among E, R, S are all E = R = S.
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.988532">
(19) He usually plays the basketball.
(20) He is playing the basketball.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.9897545">
In fact, the role of the relations among E, R, S is the same to the time marker proposed
in our time and aspect formalism. They all denote the time relation. The difference is that
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.985099">
219
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.8987632">
former is explicit, while the latter is implicit in the denotation of the reference time of an
event. Thus, to distinguish the various tense forms in English, we still need the aspect marker
to denote the progressive attribute. We summarize this result in Table 4.
Table 4
The Mapping Between (E, R. S. Aspect Marker and The Tense Form
</bodyText>
<equation confidence="0.892209615384615">
E. R. S relation aspect marker tense form
E = R = S none present
E = R = S progressive present-progressive
E &lt; R = S none present-perfect
E &lt; R = S progressive present-perfect-progressive
E = R &lt; S none past
E = R &lt; S progressive past-progressive
E &lt; R &lt; S none past-perfect
E &lt; R &lt; S progressive past-perfect-progressive
S &lt; E = R none future
S &lt; E = R progressive future-progressive
S &lt; E &lt; R none future-perfect
S &lt; E &lt; R progressive future-perfect-progressive ,
</equation>
<bodyText confidence="0.998811090909091">
Now, we can make use of Table 4 to determine the tense form of an English sentence
if we can find the E, R, S relation and the aspect marker from the Chinese sentence. As an
example, see sentence (21). In sentence (21), since the relation among E, R, S is E= R &lt; S
and the aspect marker is progressive, we have the &amp;quot;past-progressive&amp;quot; as the tense form of
the translated English sentence.
(21) zuo2-tian1 c13-shi3 ta1 zai4 kan4-shu1.
(He was reading this time yesterday.)
We have discussed the tense forms of English by E, R, S and aspect marker. However,
not all tense form can be used in a simple sentence. In a sentence containing more than one
event, the use of tense forms is further restricted. In the following sections, we will discuss
the possible tense form in a simple sentence and those in a sentence containing two evens.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.954071">
220
</page>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.996853">
3.2 Possible Tense Forms in Simple Sentences
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99997752">
In Table 2, we have listed fourteen possible tense forms of English sentences. Howev-
er, some of them can not be used in simple sentences. To discuss the possible tense forms in
sentences, we first define some terms used below. The first one is the time category. Since
time phrases contain the message of time, we partition the time phrases into four categories:
Past, Present, Future, Nondeterministic[2], according to the time these phrases represented.
The second term is the time precedence relations &amp;quot;&lt;&amp;quot;,&amp;quot;= &amp;quot;, &amp;quot; &gt; &amp;quot;, where &amp;quot; &lt; &amp;quot; represents
&amp;quot;happen before&amp;quot;; &amp;quot; &gt; &amp;quot; represents &amp;quot;happen after&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;= &amp;quot; represents &amp;quot;happen simultaneous-
ly&amp;quot;, respectively. In this section, we will discuss and give an example for each of them accord-
ing to the E, R, S formalism mentioned in the last section.
The &amp;quot;present&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;present-progressive&amp;quot; &amp;quot;present-perfect- and &amp;quot;present-perfect-
progressive&amp;quot; tense forms are all current relevant (i.e, R = S), thus they do not need time
phrases to specify their reference time. Sentences (22)-(25) show this case. The events in
&amp;quot;past&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;past-progressive&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;past-perfect&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;past-perfect-progressive&amp;quot; tense forms are
relevant to some past time, they need some phrases in Past time category to specify their refer-
ence time. Sentences (26)-(29) show such case. The word &amp;quot;qu4-nian2 ci3-shi2&amp;quot; (this time last
year) in sentence (28) specifies the reference time for the event &amp;quot;zuo4-wan2 gongl-zuo4&amp;quot;
(finish the work) and the words &amp;quot;zao3&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;yi3&amp;quot; (already) specifies that the event happened be-
fore the reference time, thus the event &amp;quot;zuo4-wan2 gongl-zuo4&amp;quot; (finish the work) happened
in the past-past time with respect to the speech time (i.e, E &lt; R &lt; S). The sentences of &amp;quot;fu-
ture&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;future-progressive&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;future-perfect&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;future-perfect-progressive&amp;quot; tense forms
usually have some phrases in Future time category to specify their reference time. The Sen-
tences (30)-(33) denote this condition. The other two tense forms &amp;quot;past-future&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;past-
future-perfect&amp;quot; are seldom used in a simple sentence. The reason is that these two tense forms
are not current relevant and there does not exist any time phrase that can both specify the
past meaning and the future meaning (relevant to the past time).
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.979339">
221
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.982692">
From above discussion, we show that we can use twelve tense forms in simple sen-
tences, some of which need time phrases to modify the events in sentences. In the following
section, we will discuss the tense forms in complex sentences.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.9287635">
(22) wo3 xi3-huan1 hua1 (I like flowers.)
(23) ta1 zai4 kan4 shu1 (He is reading now.)
(24) ta1 y13-jian1 zuo4-wan2 gong1-zuo4 1e5 (He has finished his job.)
(25) ta1 yi3-jing1 zai4 du2-shu1 1e5 (He has been reading now.)
(26) zuo2-tianl ta1 qu4 1e5 Tai2-bei3 (He went to Taipei yesterday.)
(27) zuo2-tianl c13-shi2 ta1 zai4 kan4-shu1 (He was reading this time yesterday.)
(28) qu4-nian2 ci3-shi2 wo3 zao3 yi3 zuo4-wan2 gong1-zuo4 le5 (This time last year,
I had finished my job. )
(29) qu4-nian2 ci3-shi2 wo3 zao3 yi3 zai4 kan4-shu1 (This time last year. I had been
reading.)
(30) ming2-tianl ta1 jiang1 qu4 Tai2-bei3 (He will go to Taipei tomorrow.)
(31) ming2-tian2 ci3 shi2 wo3 jiang1 zai4 kan4-shul (I will be reading this time tomorrow.)
(32) ming2-nian2 ci3-shi3 ta1 jiang1 yi3 bi4-yeh4 (He will have graduated this time next
year.)
(33) ming2-nian2 ci3-shi2 ta1 jiang1 yi3-jing1 zai4 zhun3-bei4 kao3-shi4 1e5 (He will
have been preparing the examination this time next year.)
</figure>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.871279">
33 Possible Tense Forms in Sentences with Two Events
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.99967675">
As we have analyzed in the last section, we can use one of the twelve tense forms to
represent a simple sentence. When there are two events in a sentence, the tense forms of these
events can not be any combination of the twelve tense forms. however. There may have some
new tense forms such as &amp;quot;past-future&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;past-future-perfect&amp;quot; which can not be used in
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.969156">
222
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999555909090909">
the simple sentence. There may also have some illegal combinations such as {past, present—
progressive} as in the sentence &amp;quot;When I came in, he is eating his lunch.&amp;quot;. The requirement
of correct combination for tense forms in a sentence is called tense agreement.
Some people define the tense agreement as that the tense forms in a sentence should
be the same, as the sentence (34) shows. The sentence (34) is correct because the tense form
of the verbs &amp;quot;knew&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;read&amp;quot; are the same while (35) is illegal because the tense forms of
the verbs &amp;quot;knew&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;reads&amp;quot; are different. Some might think that the tense form of the sub-
ordinate clause should follows that of the main clause (such as the sentence (34) shows), or
that the tense form of the main clause should follows that of the subordinate clause (such as
the sentence (36) shows). However, these still have deficiencies[6]. They can not explain the
correct sentence shown as sentence (37).
</bodyText>
<listItem confidence="0.94728625">
(34) I knew that he read a book.
(35) *I knew that he reads a book.
(36) The boy I talked to had blue eyes.
(37) The boy I grew up with is the president of America.
</listItem>
<bodyText confidence="0.868513444444444">
Lin &amp; Chen[7] made some notes about the tense agreement in English. They claimed
that in a complex sentence, if the main clause has the tense form of&amp;quot; present&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;future&amp;quot;, or
&amp;quot;present—perfect&amp;quot;, the tense form for the subordinate clause can be any of the twelve tense
forms mentioned above. When the tense form of the main clause is &amp;quot;past&amp;quot;, change the tense
forms of the subordinate clause to the past form. Thus, the tense forms of the two clauses
in a sentence may be any one in Table 5, ignoring the progressive aspect in the main clause.
Table 5
Possible Tense Forms for Sentences Containing
tense form of main clause tense of subordinate clause
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99164">
223
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993666482758621">
present, present-perfect present, present-progressive
future, or future-perfect present-perfect
present-perfect-progressive
past, past-progressive,
past-perfect,
past-perfect-progressive
future, future-progressive
future-perfect
future-perfect-progressive
past, past-perfect past, past-progressive,
past-perfect,
past-perfect-progressive
past-future. past-future-perfect
Now, we consider the situations in Chinese. Taking sentence (38) as an example, the
main clause has &amp;quot;past&amp;quot; as its tense form while its subordinate clause has the &amp;quot;past-future&amp;quot;
tense form.
(38) tal zuo2-tianl dal-ying4 wo3 lai2 zhe4-1i3.
(He promised me yesterday that he would come here.)
(He allowed me to come yesterday.)
To find out the possible combinations of the tense forms for the two clauses in a sen-
tence, we divide our domain into six parts, i.e., (a) nondeterministic, (b) E2 &gt; El, (c) E2 &lt;
El in serial verb construction sentences and (d) El &amp;quot;de5 shi2-hou4&amp;quot; (when) E2&amp;quot;, (e) El
&amp;quot;yi3-qian2&amp;quot; (before) E2, and El &amp;quot;yi3-hou4&amp;quot; (after) E2[2].
(a). nondeterministic for verbs in serial verb constructions
The possible tense forms of the events in sentences of serial verb constructions will
be the same to those in Table 5. The reason is that the two events in the sentence have no
predetermined relation. Thus, any possible relation is permitted to exist between them. For
example, the combinations {present, present-perfect}. {future. present) are all legal as sen-
tences (39)-(40) show.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988489">
224
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.966261230769231">
(39) wo3 zhi1-dao4 ta1 y13-ying1 qu4 r14-ben3 1e5.
(I know that he has gone to Japan.)
(40) ming3-tian1 ta1 jiang1 zhi1-dao4 Zhang1san1 xi3-huan1 Al-Hua1.
(Tomorrow he will know that Zhangsan likes A-Hua.)
(b). E2 &gt; El
The possible tense forms of the clauses in sentences of such kind are more restricted
since the relation between the two events is specified. We list the possible combinations of
tense forms for them in Table 6 and use the sentence (41) to illustrate it. In sentence (41),
the tense forms for the verbs &amp;quot;dal-ying4&amp;quot; (promise) and &amp;quot;lai2&amp;quot; (come) are &amp;quot;past-perfect&amp;quot; and
&amp;quot;past-future&amp;quot; respectively.
(41) ta1 zao3 yi3 dal-ying4 wo3 lai2 zhe4-113.
(He had promised me that he would come here.)
(He had allowed me to come here.)
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.676026">
Table 6
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.902568333333333">
Possible Tense Forms for El and E2 in E2 &gt; El
tense form of El tense form of E2
present future
present-progressive future
present-perfect future
present-perfect-progressive future
past past-future
past-progressive past-future
past-perfect past-future
past-perfect-progressive past-future
future future
future-progressive future
future-perfect future
future-perfect-progressive future
(c) E2 &lt; El
</figure>
<page confidence="0.987946">
225
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.992715">
The possible tense forms of the events in sentences of such kind are also restricted
as those of E2 &gt; El. We list the possible combinations of tense forms for them in Table 7
and illustrate it by the sentence (42). In sentence (42), the tense forms for the predicates
&amp;quot;pil-ping2&amp;quot; (criticize), &amp;quot;lan3-duo4&amp;quot; (lazy) are &amp;quot;past&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;past-perfect&amp;quot; respectively.
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.63311805882353">
(42) tal wo3 tai4 lan3-duo4.
( He criticized that I had been too lazy. )
Table 7
fossible Tense Forms for El and E2 in E2 &lt; El
tense form of El tense form of E2
present past
present-progressive past
present-perfect past
present--perfect-progressive past
past past-perfect
past-progressive past-perfect
past-perfect past-perfect
past-perfect-progressive past-perfect
future past
future-progressive past
future-perfect past
future-perfect-progressive past
</figure>
<bodyText confidence="0.999875125">
The roles of events El and E2 in serial verb construction sentences are different from
those of El&apos; and E2&apos; in sentences linked by linking element. In fact, the clause containing
the event El is the main clause and the clause containing the event E2 is the subordinate
clause, while the clause containing the event El&apos; is the main clause and the clause containing
the event E2&apos; is the subordinate clause. As we have mentioned in Sec. 3.2, there are twelve
possible tense forms for the main clause of the sentence and the tense form of the subordinate
clause may be determined by the time relation between El and E2. However, any time phrase
in the subordinate clause may change the reference time for E2. Thus, we can hardly use the
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.991799">
226
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.988587391304348">
event time of El as the reference time of E2. For example, the reference time of verb &amp;quot;lai2&amp;quot;
(come) in sentence (43) is not the event time of &amp;quot;da3-suan4&amp;quot; (propose) but some time in to-
morrow.
(43) tal da3-suan4 ming2-tianl 1a12.
( He proposes to come tomorrow.)
On the contrary, in sentences linked by &amp;quot;de5 shi2-hou4&amp;quot; (when), &amp;quot;yi3-hou4&amp;quot; (after),
&amp;quot;yi3-qian2&amp;quot; (before), the possible tense form of the event E2&apos; can be usually determined by
the relations of E, R, S. This is because in sentences of such cases, the event time of El&apos; can
be used as the reference time for the event E2&apos;. In the following paragraph, we denote the
event times of El&apos; and E2&apos; as El and E2, respectively. We also denote the speech time as
S and the reference time for the event E2 as R2. We analyze them as follows:
(d).E1 de5 shi2-hou4 E2
(i) If the tense form of the event El&apos; is &amp;quot;past&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;past-progressive&amp;quot;, the event time
of El (i.e., El or say, R2) is past. Thus, we have R2 &lt; S. From Table 4, we have four pairs
of { E, R, S relation, aspect} : E2 = R2 &lt; S, none 1, 1 E2 = R2 &lt; S, progressive 1, { E2
&lt; R2 &lt; S, none }, { E2 = R2 &lt; S, progressive } with the corresponding tense forms &amp;quot;past&amp;quot;,
&amp;quot;past-progressive&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;past-perfect&amp;quot;, and &amp;quot;past-perfect-progressive&amp;quot; for E2&apos;.
(ii) If the tense form of the event El&apos; is &amp;quot;future&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;future-progressive&amp;quot;, the event
time of El&apos; is future. Thus, we have S &lt;R2 . From Table 4, we have four pairs of {E, R, S
relation, aspect marker} : S &lt; E2 = R2, none 1, 1 S &lt; E2 = R2, progressive 1, 1 S &lt;
E2 &lt; R2 , none 1, S &lt; E2 &lt; R2, progressive 1. From these pairs, we can get the possible
tense forms: &amp;quot;future&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;future-progressive&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;future-perfect&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;future-perfect-progres-
sive&amp;quot; for E2&apos;.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988507">
227
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.998638777777778">
(iii) lithe tense form of the event El&apos; is &amp;quot;present&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;present-progressive&amp;quot;, the event
time is viewed as the same to S (i.e., E1 = S). That is, R2 = S. Thus, we have the pairs of
{E, R, S relation, aspect}: E2 = R2 = S, none 1, E1 = R2 = S. progressive} and E2&apos; may
possess the tense forms: &amp;quot;present&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;present-progressive&amp;quot;.
We summarize the results in Table 8 and give three sentences (44)-(46) with the tense
forms as examples. One might find that some of the tense forms in the English sentences has
been changed. For example, the tense form of the verb &amp;quot;lai2&amp;quot; (come) in sentence (45) is &amp;quot;pres-
ent&amp;quot; while its original tense form is &amp;quot;future&amp;quot;. This phenomena is due to the convention of
English. We will discuss them in the next section.
</bodyText>
<table confidence="0.853647571428571">
(44) zuo2-tianl tal lai2 de5 shi2-hou4, wo3 zai4 kan4-shul.
( When he came yesterday, I was reading. ) {El&apos;:past, E2&apos;:past-progressive}
(45) tal lai2 de5 shi2-hou4, wo3 jiangl kail men2.
( When he comes, I will open the door. ) {EV:future, E2&apos;:future}
(46) mei3 ci4 wo3 zai4 kan4 shul de5 shi2-hou4, tal doul zai4 shui4-jiao4.
(Every time when I&apos;m reading, he is sleeping.)(EV:present-progressive, E2&apos;:present-
progressive)
</table>
<tableCaption confidence="0.974436">
Table 8
</tableCaption>
<subsectionHeader confidence="0.296982">
Possible Tense Forms for El&apos; and E2&apos; in Er de5 shi2-hou4 E2&apos;
</subsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.995715625">
tense form of El
past
past-progressive
future
future-progressive
present
tense form of E2
past, past-progressive,
past-perfect, past-perfect-progressive
past, past-progressive,
past-perfect, past-perfect-progressive
future, future progressive.
future-perfect, future-perfect-progressive
future, future progressive.
future-perfect. future-perfect-progressive
present. present-progressive
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.988868">
228
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.883611777777778">
present-progressive present. present-progressive
(e). El&apos; yi3-qian2 (before) E2&apos;
In this case, the relation between El&apos; and E2&apos; is specified. This relation restricts the
possible combinations of the tense forms for El&apos; and E2&apos;.
(i )If the event time of El&apos; is past (i.e. El = R2 &lt; S), we have the relation E2 &lt;
R2 &lt; S. Thus, the tense forms for E2&apos; may be &amp;quot;past-perfect&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;past-perfect-progressive&amp;quot;,
as the sentence (47) shows.
(47) wo3 qu4 Tai2-bei3 y13-qian2 mai3 1e5 yi4 ben3 shul.
( I had bought a book before I went to Taipei. )
(ii) If the event time of El&apos; is future (i.e., S &lt;E1 = R2), we have the relation S &lt;E2
&lt;R2 .Thus, the tense forms for E2&apos; may be &amp;quot;future-perfect&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;future-perfect-progres-
sive&amp;quot;. Sentence (48) illustrates such a example.
(48) wo3. qu4 Tai2-bei3 yi3-qian2 jiangl yi3 zuo4-wan2 gongl-zuo4 le5.
( I will have finished my job before I come to Taipei. )
We also summarize the possible combinations of tense forms in Table 9.
Table 9
Possible Tense Forms for El and E2 in El yi3-qian2 E2
tense form of El tense form of E2
</bodyText>
<figure confidence="0.421649">
past past-perfect
past past-perfect-progressive
future future-perfect
future future-perfect-progressive
(f) El yi3-hou4 E2
</figure>
<page confidence="0.993983">
229
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9463339375">
In this condition the relation between El&apos; and E2&apos; is E1 &lt; E2. There are two cases:
(i) If the event time of El&apos; is past (i.e., E1 = R2 &lt; S), we have the relation R2 &lt; E2
&lt; S. However, there is no such case in Table 4. Therefore, we have to make some changes.
Intuitively, the event E2&apos; happened before the speech time, thus we may give the tense form
of E2&apos; &amp;quot;past&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;past-progressive&amp;quot;. The event El&apos; happened before E2&apos;, i.e., it happened
in the past-past with respect to the speech time. It possesses the &amp;quot;past-perfect&amp;quot; as its tense
form. The sentence (49) shows a good example.
(49) tal lai2 zhe4-1i3 y13-hou4 mai3 1e5 y14 ben3 shul.
( He bought a book after he had come here. )
(ii) If the event time of El&apos; is future (i.e., S &lt; E1 = R2 ), we have the relation: S &lt;R2
&lt; E2 . Still, there is no such case in Table 4. The obvious solution to this case is to set the
tense forms for El&apos; and E2&apos; as {future-perfect, future} or {future-perfect, future-progres-
sive}. See sentence (50) as an example.
(50) tal lai2 zhe4-113 y13-hou4 jiangl mai3 yi4 ben3 shul.
( He will buy a book after he comes here. )
The result is summarized in Table 10.
</bodyText>
<tableCaption confidence="0.664111">
Table 10
</tableCaption>
<figure confidence="0.703146">
Possible Tense Forms for El and E2 in El yi3-hou4 E2
tense form of El tense form of E2
past-perfect past
past-perfect past-progressive
future-perfect future
future-perfect future-progressive
</figure>
<page confidence="0.97051">
230
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.780081666666667">
In this section, we have discussed the combinations of tense forms in sentences con-
taining two events. However, there are some conventions in English that may change the
tense forms of English sentences. We will discuss them in the next section.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.650204" genericHeader="method">
4. Some Conventional Rules in English for Translation
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.941484809523809">
When translating a Chinese sentence into English, the sentence pattern and the syn-
tactic roles of corresponding words may be changed. In this paper, we assume a verb in Chi-
nese sentence is translated into a verb in English. In most sentences, this assumption is cor-
rect.
&amp;yule tense forms in English need be modified according to other world knowledge.
For example, the sentence
* (51a) Einstein has visited Princeton.
is incorrect because Einstein is dead, but sentence (51b) is correct.
(51b) Einstein visited Princeton.
In this paper, we propose a rule-checking method to solve this problem. After we gen-
erate the tense form, we test the tense forms to see whether they satisfy the following rules
to avoid errors. We list some of them below[6,7].
(a). If the tense form we get is &amp;quot;present-perfect&amp;quot; and the person referred by the subject is
dead, then change the tense form to &amp;quot;past&amp;quot;. Sentence(51b) is an example.
(b). If the tense form is &amp;quot;present-perfect&amp;quot; and the time phrase is given specially, use &amp;quot;past&amp;quot;
tense form instead. Take sentence(52) as an example.
(52) tal zou2-tianl yi3-jingl qu4 1e5 Tai2-bei3 1e5.
* ( He has gone to Taipei yesterday. )
( He went to Taipei yesterday. )
(c). If two clauses are linked by the conjunction &amp;quot;before&amp;quot; r &amp;quot;after&amp;quot;, the tense form &amp;quot;past-
past&amp;quot; can be changed to &amp;quot;past&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;past-future-past&amp;quot; to &amp;quot;past-future&amp;quot;. It is because the con-
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.981034">
231
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.985792">
junction &amp;quot;after&amp;quot; or &amp;quot;before&amp;quot; is sufficient to indicate the relation between the two clauses it
connects. As an example, see sentence (53).
(53) wo3 zuo4-wan2 gongl-zou4 yi3-hou4, cai2 chil wan3-fan4.
( I ate my dinner after I had finished my job. )
( I ate my dinner after I finished my job. )
(d). In subordinate clause, such as when-clause, if-clause, and so on, .replace the &amp;quot;future&amp;quot;
tense form by the &amp;quot;present&amp;quot; tense form. Sentence(54) shows such an example.
(54) dangl chunl-tianl lai2 de5 shi2-hou4, yan4-zi5 jiu4 hui4 hui2-1a12.
* ( When the spring will come, the swallows will return. )
( When the spring comes, the swallows will return. )
(e). If the tense form of the main clause is &amp;quot;past&amp;quot; and the statement in the subordinate clause
is a fact or a truth, the tense form of the subordinate clause is set to &amp;quot;present&amp;quot;. The sentence
(55) illustrates this convention. However, this rule is difficult to implement because the main-
tenance of the world knowledge is hard.
(55) wo3 gao4-su4 tal cheng2-shi3 wei2 shang4 ce4.
( I told him that honest was the best policy. )
( I told him that honest is the best policy. )
To further demonstrate the applicability of above rules, we analyze sentence (56) in
detail.
(56) tal dal-ying4 wo3 zai4 wo3 1i2-kail y13-qin2, qian3 wo3 chil wan3-fan4.
The time markers for verbs &amp;quot;dal -ying4&amp;quot; (promise), &amp;quot;H2-kai1 (leave) and &amp;quot;chil&amp;quot; (eat)
in the sentence are past, past-future and past-future-past, corresponding to the tense forms
&amp;quot;past,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;past-future&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;past-future-perfect&amp;quot; respectively. By rule (c), the tense form of
the verb &amp;quot;chil wan3-fan4&amp;quot; (eat dinner) is changed to &amp;quot;past-future&amp;quot; (that is, item 9 of Table
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.950787">
232
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.999775333333333">
2) since there is a conjunction &amp;quot;before.&amp;quot; By rule (d), the tense form &amp;quot;past-future&amp;quot; of &amp;quot;112-kail&amp;quot;
(leave) is changed to &amp;quot;past.&amp;quot; In summary, the tense forms of verbs &amp;quot;dal -ying4&amp;quot; (promise),
&amp;quot;112-kail &amp;quot; (leave) and &amp;quot;chil &amp;quot; (eat) are changes to &apos;past,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;past,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;past-future&amp;quot; respectively:
Because there are several ways to express the future tense of a verb, we still have to select
the representation of its tense forms. Finally, the sentence generated would be &amp;quot;He promised,
that he would give me a dinner before I left.&amp;quot;
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997227" genericHeader="conclusions">
5. CONCLUSION
</sectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999980875">
The paper has presented a preliminary analysis of possible tense forms in both simple
sentences and complex sentences through the ERS model. We have found that different sen-
tential structures may have different tense forms for the predicates in sentences. Thus, we may
predict the possible tense forms from the structure or the linking element possessed by the
sentence.
The problem in this paper is restricted by the-domain anyway. The analysis and imple-
mentation of the tense forms for simple sentences have been done. However, we still have
a long way to go for more complex sentences, discourse, and so on.
</bodyText>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.997933" genericHeader="references">
REFERENCES
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.932119">
1..C. N. Li and S. A. Thompson, Mandarin Chinese: A Functional Reference Grammar, Taipei:
Wen-He Pub., 1983.
2..H. J. Lee and R. R. Hsu, &amp;quot;The analysis of tense and aspect in Chinese sentences for translat-
ing mechanically to English,&amp;quot; Proc. 1990 Intern. Conf on Computer Proc. of Chinese and
Oriental Languages, Hunan, 1990, pp.21-26.
3..T. Winograd, Language as a Cognitive Process, Addison-Wesley Pub., 1983.
4..H. Reichenbach, The Elements of Symbolic Logic, New York: The Free Press, 1966.
5..B. L. Webber, &amp;quot;Forward,&amp;quot; Computational Linguistics, Vol. 14. No. 2, June 1988.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.931909">
233
</page>
<reference confidence="0.97675775">
6..X. E Huang, Mastering Modern English Grammar, (in Chinese), Taipei: Wen-He Pub.,
1982.
7..C. S. Lin and Y. Z. Chen, A New Standard English Grammar, (in Chinese), Tainan: Dai-
Shan Pub., 1987.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.994275">
234
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="AAMatching" version="110505">
  <results time="1337274044" date="Fri May 18 01:00:44 SGT 2012">
    <authors>
      <author>
        <fullname source="parscit">Hsi, Jian Lee</fullname>
        <institutions>
          <institution>Department of Computer Science and Information Engineering</institution>
        </institutions>
      </author>
      <author>
        <fullname source="parscit">Ren, Rong Hsu R O C</fullname>
        <institutions>
          <institution>Department of Computer Science and Information Engineering</institution>
        </institutions>
      </author>
    </authors>
    <institutions>
      <institution>Department of Computer Science and Information Engineering</institution>
      <institution>National Chiao Tung University</institution>
      <institution>Hsinchu, Taiwan, 30050</institution>
    </institutions>
  </results>
</algorithm>

</algorithms>