<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<algorithms version="110505">
<algorithm name="SectLabel" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.010094">
<title confidence="0.94184">
Investigating Discourse Relations
</title>
<author confidence="0.877849">
Megan Moser
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.802834">
University of Pittsburgh
Learning Research and Development Center
</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.255033">
Pittsburgh, PA 15260
</address>
<email confidence="0.417074">
moserOpogo.isp.pitt.cdu
</email>
<author confidence="0.520422">
Johanna D. Moore
</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.8354965">
University of Pittsburgh
Department of Computer Science, and
Learning Research and Development Center
Pittsburgh, PA 15260
</affiliation>
<subsubsectionHeader confidence="0.168856">
jntoorr Ocs.pitt.cdu
</subsubsectionHeader>
<bodyText confidence="0.999936184210526">
In this paper, we present the theoretical foundations which underlie our current research. We
emphasize a methodological point: connections among proposed theories of discourse structure must
be carefully explicated. By making these connections, we can determine whether theories make
equivalent claims, consistent but unrelated claims or differ in substantive issues. A synthesis of
current theories is required, a descriptive framework which assumes the common ground and which
highlights issues to be resolved. Further, there are two distinct factors to guide us in developing
such a synthesis. First, the descriptive framework must facilitate the formulation of controversial
issues in terms of empirical predictions. Then, the ,synthesis can be developed and refined by
linguistic studies. Second, the framework must be applicable to computer processing of natural
language, both understanding and generation. Our particular interest is the computer generation
of explanations in a tutoring system. Ideally, the framework will provide a means through which
the results of discourse analysis and computational linguistics can inform one another.
In its broadest outline, the goal is to understand the precise interaction between features of
form, meaning and function in the creation of discourse coherence. What kind of form, meaning
and function links occur between utterances and how are these three kinds of links recognized? In
a first step towards the synthesis we would like to see, we will discuss the perspective which the
GXLS (Grosz and Sidner 1986) and RST (=Rhetorical Structure Theory, Mann and Thompson 1988)
theories take on links of meaning and function. We conclude with a brief description of an empirical
study suggested by this theory comparison. Note that we consider only monologic discourse at this
time, believing generalizations between this and multi-agent discourse to be premature.
In the study and discussion of rhetorical relations, the terminology has become nonstandard
and confusing. Here, we adopt the term &amp;quot;discourse relations&amp;quot; to mean all tIne connections among
the expressions in discourse which, taken together, account for its coherence. So, in order to be
a discourse relation in the sense used here, two criteria are required. One, the relation concerns
elements of a sentence utterance and other utterances in the context. Two, the relation must be
recognized in order to understand the discourse, i.e., it contributes to coherence rather than another
concern such as style. As suggested above, sonic feature of form, meaning or function defines a
discourse relation. These will be termed textual, informational and intentional discourse relations
respectively. Informational and intentional discourse relations are essentially non-linguistic in the
sense that they do not originate with language. Mn`ch recent work on discourse relations either
explicitly discusses or implictly uses a distinction between informational and intentional relations
(Schiffrin 1987, Redeker 1990, Hovy and Maier 1992, Moore and Pollack 1992, Moser 1992, Sanders,
Spooren and Noordman 1992, inter alia). The distinction, a kind of semantic-pragmatic distinction,
concerns the source of discourse relations, whether a relation orginates with what is being talked
about (informational) or with why we are talking about it (intentional). Informational discourse
relations arise because the meanings of expressions in utterances, the things being talked about,
stand in some relation in the domain of discourse. CAUSE, for example, is an informational relation
because it is a relation between things that are being talked about, the fact of one situation or
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.99653">
94
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.993285145833333">
event causing another. Intentional relations, in contrast, concern how one span is intended to affect
the hearer&apos;s mental attitude about another, i.e., why the speaker included some span of text. For
example, the EVIDENCE relation holds between two text spans if one is intended to increase the
hearer&apos;s belief in the other.
G&amp;S take a speaker&apos;s plan to be the source of discourse structure. A general intention may
dominate several subintentions which may themselves be further refilled. At the bottom of the
hierarchical structure are intentions which are realized by producing utterances in the discourse.
Intentions higher in the intention structure are realized by the subintentions they dominate and,
possibly, additional utterances which express the higher level intention. Intentions are related by
dominance, when one intention generates one or more subintentions, or by satisfaction-precedence,
when the realization of one intention is a precondition for the realization of another. In this theory,
spans of text are related indirectly by the relations between the intentions they realize.
In the original formulation of RST, the informational-intentional distinction was noted (there
called &amp;quot;subject matter&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;presentational&amp;quot; relations), but wa.s not, fully appreciated. Text is
hierarchically structured and exactly one RST relation is postulated between contiguous spans.
Moore and Pollack (1992) propose that, in fact, two contiguous spans of text may be in both
an informational and an intentional relation simultaneously and that recognition of one kind of
relation can facilitate recognition of the other. They note that intentional relations arise because
&amp;quot;consecutive discourse elements are related to one another by means of the ways in which they
participate in [a speaker&apos;s] plan.&amp;quot; (p. 2). An intentional relation indicates both a direction of effect
and a kind of effect. Both elements of an intentional relation in R.ST correspond to elements in the
relations among intentions in Clk,S.
First of all, one span is contributed with the intention of affecting the purpose of another
span. In the original RST with only a. single relation between spans, the direction of the relation
(from satellite to nucleus) always represented the direction of effect. In introducing simultaneous
intentional and informational relations, nuclearity is an aspect of intentional relations only. The
direction of an intentional relation in RST corresponds to dominance in GkS. That is, the satellite
span, S, affects the purpose of the nucleus span, N, only if the intention that S realizes is dominated
by the intention that S and N (and possibly others) realize together.
Second of all, in R,ST, one span is intended to affect another in one of several ways. For example,
a satellite span, S, may be intended to affect a, hearer&apos;s belief in the nucleus span, N, (the EVIDENCE
relation); or S may be intended to affect a hearer&apos;s desire to perform the action indicated by N
(the MOTIVATION relation). Correspondingly in GkS, intentions of various kinds may dominate
other intentions. Roughly speaking, intentions realized by speaking are to either affect a hearer&apos;s
beliefs or her actions. An RST EVIDENCE relation can occur only when the dominating intention
is to affect another&apos;s belief. Similarly, an RST MOTIVATION relation can occur only when the
dominating intention is to affect another&apos;s action. Thus the different kinds of intentional effects in
RST correspond to different kinds of dominating intentions in G&amp;S. However, RST makes more
distinctions among kinds of effects than G&amp;S, e.g., both EVIDENCE and JUSTIFICATION are ways of
affecting beliefs and both MOTIVATION and ENABLEMENT are ways of affecting actions.
Now we turn to the status of informational relations in the two theories. In RST, a single
informational relation is assigned between spans of text. As a, result, RST informational relations
concern the sorts of entities denoted by entire spans, such as situations and events. If we adopt
the view of Moore and Pollack, recognizing that informational and intentional relations occur
simultaneously, the informational relations are simplified. As noted above, nuclearity, which was
an element of the unique RST relation between spans N and 5, is now an element, of the intentional
relation and is independent of the informational relation. That is, informational relations no longer
conflate the semantic link between situations expressed by two spans :itid the dominance of speaker
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.997886">
95
</page>
<bodyText confidence="0.9999834375">
intentions realized by those spans. In fact, without this conflation, it is unclear whether the semantic
relations between situations and events is in principle different from semantic links between other
kinds of entities. Is the informational relation between two spans of text necessarily a relation
between the entire spans? Or, is it possible that the informational relation is a series of links
between various expressions contained in the spans? Examples of these links between smaller
constituents are would are coreference and a. causal link between expressions such as &amp;quot;run a red
light&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;the ticket.&amp;quot;
GkS stresses that intentions of the speaker are the primary source of discourse structure. Do-
main knowledge plays a role in recognizing the intentional structure, but it is doubtful whether any
special distinction would be made between knowledge about events and situations and knowledge
about other kinds of domain entities.
In comparing the status of intentional and infbrinational discourse relations in both RST and
GkS, at least two issues were specified whose resolution is currently presumed by both theories
in isolation. First, what types of dominance are distinguished by the theory— just dominance,
dominance by belief-affecting intention versus dominance by action-affecting intention, or the full
range of RST intentional relations? Second, do semantic links between whole spans of text play
a. role in the theory, or do semantic relations between all sorts of entities have the same status?
Both these questions can be answered separately depending on whether they are meant as a ques-
tion about linguistic theory or about its application to language processing. Space precludes a
discussion of textual discourse relations as yell a,s questions about how the three kinds of relations
interact. Further, proposals from linguists (Schiffrin 1987; Redeker 1992) must be integrated into
the synthesis.
We conclude by sketching a discourse analysis study which begins to address the first question
cited above, one which we plan to do. Using a broad range of text types, we select as tokens the
pairs of spans that are related by lexical markers of discourse relations such as &amp;quot;so,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;because&amp;quot; and
&amp;quot;therefore.&amp;quot; For each token, we code the informational and intentional relations that co-occur with
it. As emphasized by Moore and Paris (1992), there is not a one-to-one mapping between intentional
and informational relations. Though not completely independent, the possibilities for informational
relations given the occurrence of a particular intentional relation are many, and vice versa. By
investigating the range of combinations of informational and intentional relations which occur
with a lexical marker, we can identify the minimal description of the marker in tennis of discourse
relations. That is, we can see whether a. marker correlates highly with a particular disconrse relation
or combination of informational and intentional relations. Such a. study will produce results that
are useful for computational models of both natural language understanding and generation. If
a certain marker correlates highly with certain discourse relations, the understander can form
hypotheses about the discourse relations that are present when it encounters a. marker. Similarly,
if a generator must express two utterances connected by a. certain combination of relations, it can
use the information about the correlation between markers and combinations of discourse relations
to choose the most appropriate marker.
In addition, this study will allow its to determine whether the distinction among types of
dominance plays a. role in accounting for the distribution of markers. If the study confirms the
relevance of this distinction, then dominance types have a. role to play in a. linguistic theory of
discourse coherence. If the study does not confirm the distinction, a. crucial theoretical question is
whether there is any direct formal linguistic pattern other than these markers that makes essential
use of dominance types in its description. Should further research fail to identify such a pattern,
then the status of dominance types in linguistic theory is called into question. However, even if it
turns out that dominance types are not formally marked by language, it remains an open question
whether their application to computer generation and understanding will be useful.
</bodyText>
<page confidence="0.989194">
96
</page>
<sectionHeader confidence="0.996468" genericHeader="abstract">
References
</sectionHeader>
<reference confidence="0.999993818181818">
[1] Grosz, B., 1978. Focusing in Dialog, Tinlap-2: Theoretical Issues in Natural Language Pro-
cessing 7: 96-103. New York: Association for Computing Machinery and Association of Compu-
tational Linguistics.
[2] Grosz, B. J. and Sidner, C. L., 1986. Attention, intention, and the structure of discourse.
Computational Linguistics 12(3):175-204.
[3] Hovy, E. and E. Maier, 1992. Parsimonious or Profligate: How Many and Which Discourse
Structure Relations. ms. Submitted for publication.
[4] Mann, W. C. and Thompson, S. A., 1988. Rhetorical Structure Theory: Towards a functional
theory of text organization. TEXT 8(3):243-281.
[5] Moore, J. D. and Pollack, M. E., 1992. A problem for RST: The need for multi-level discourse
analysis. Computational Linguistics 18(4).
[6] Moore, J. D. and Paris, C. L., 1992. Planning Text For Advisory Dialogues: Capturing Inten-
tional and Rhetorical Information. University of Pittsburgh, Department of Computer Science
Technical Report Number 92-22. Submitted for publication.
[7] Moser, M., 1992. Analysis of conversational arguments. Presentation to Washington Linguistics
Society, Washington, DC, November 12. Working paper.
[8] Redeker, G., 1992. Coherence and Structure in Text and Discourse. ins. Under review.
[9] Redeker, G., 1990. Ideational and Pragmatic Markers of Discourse Structure. Journal of
Pragmatics 14: 367-81.
[10] Sanders, T. J. M., W. P. M. S. Spooren and L. G. M. Noordman, 1992. Towards a Taxonomy
of Coherence Relations. Discourse Processes 15: 1-35.
[11] Schiffrin, D., 1987. Discourse Markers. Cambridge: Cambridge .University Press.
</reference>
<page confidence="0.999694">
97
</page>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsHed" version="110505">
<variant no="0" confidence="0.066209">
<title confidence="0.999749">Investigating Discourse Relations</title>
<author confidence="0.999984">Megan Moser</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.982899">University of Learning Research and Development</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.602696">Pittsburgh, PA</address>
<email confidence="0.991343">moserOpogo.isp.pitt.cdu</email>
<author confidence="0.995613">Johanna D Moore</author>
<affiliation confidence="0.996962666666667">University of Department of Computer Science, Learning Research and Development</affiliation>
<address confidence="0.951175">Pittsburgh, PA</address>
<abstract confidence="0.998053729927007">jntoorr Ocs.pitt.cdu In this paper, we present the theoretical foundations which underlie our current research. We emphasize a methodological point: connections among proposed theories of discourse structure must be carefully explicated. By making these connections, we can determine whether theories make equivalent claims, consistent but unrelated claims or differ in substantive issues. A synthesis of current theories is required, a descriptive framework which assumes the common ground and which highlights issues to be resolved. Further, there are two distinct factors to guide us in developing such a synthesis. First, the descriptive framework must facilitate the formulation of controversial in terms of empirical predictions. Then, the can be developed and refined by linguistic studies. Second, the framework must be applicable to computer processing of natural language, both understanding and generation. Our particular interest is the computer generation of explanations in a tutoring system. Ideally, the framework will provide a means through which the results of discourse analysis and computational linguistics can inform one another. In its broadest outline, the goal is to understand the precise interaction between features of form, meaning and function in the creation of discourse coherence. What kind of form, meaning and function links occur between utterances and how are these three kinds of links recognized? In a first step towards the synthesis we would like to see, we will discuss the perspective which the GXLS (Grosz and Sidner 1986) and RST (=Rhetorical Structure Theory, Mann and Thompson 1988) theories take on links of meaning and function. We conclude with a brief description of an empirical study suggested by this theory comparison. Note that we consider only monologic discourse at this time, believing generalizations between this and multi-agent discourse to be premature. In the study and discussion of rhetorical relations, the terminology has become nonstandard and confusing. Here, we adopt the term &amp;quot;discourse relations&amp;quot; to mean all tIne connections among the expressions in discourse which, taken together, account for its coherence. So, in order to be a discourse relation in the sense used here, two criteria are required. One, the relation concerns elements of a sentence utterance and other utterances in the context. Two, the relation must be recognized in order to understand the discourse, i.e., it contributes to coherence rather than another concern such as style. As suggested above, sonic feature of form, meaning or function defines a discourse relation. These will be termed textual, informational and intentional discourse relations respectively. Informational and intentional discourse relations are essentially non-linguistic in the sense that they do not originate with language. Mn`ch recent work on discourse relations either explicitly discusses or implictly uses a distinction between informational and intentional relations (Schiffrin 1987, Redeker 1990, Hovy and Maier 1992, Moore and Pollack 1992, Moser 1992, Sanders, Spooren and Noordman 1992, inter alia). The distinction, a kind of semantic-pragmatic distinction, concerns the source of discourse relations, whether a relation orginates with what is being talked about (informational) or with why we are talking about it (intentional). Informational discourse relations arise because the meanings of expressions in utterances, the things being talked about, in some relation in the domain of discourse. example, is an informational relation because it is a relation between things that are being talked about, the fact of one situation or 94 event causing another. Intentional relations, in contrast, concern how one span is intended to affect the hearer&apos;s mental attitude about another, i.e., why the speaker included some span of text. For the holds between two text spans if one is intended to increase the hearer&apos;s belief in the other. G&amp;S take a speaker&apos;s plan to be the source of discourse structure. A general intention may dominate several subintentions which may themselves be further refilled. At the bottom of the hierarchical structure are intentions which are realized by producing utterances in the discourse. Intentions higher in the intention structure are realized by the subintentions they dominate and, additional utterances which express the higher level intention. Intentions are related dominance, when one intention generates one or more subintentions, or by satisfaction-precedence, when the realization of one intention is a precondition for the realization of another. In this theory, spans of text are related indirectly by the relations between the intentions they realize. In the original formulation of RST, the informational-intentional distinction was noted (there called &amp;quot;subject matter&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;presentational&amp;quot; relations), but wa.s not, fully appreciated. Text is hierarchically structured and exactly one RST relation is postulated between contiguous spans. Moore and Pollack (1992) propose that, in fact, two contiguous spans of text may be in both an informational and an intentional relation simultaneously and that recognition of one kind of relation can facilitate recognition of the other. They note that intentional relations arise because &amp;quot;consecutive discourse elements are related to one another by means of the ways in which they participate in [a speaker&apos;s] plan.&amp;quot; (p. 2). An intentional relation indicates both a direction of effect and a kind of effect. Both elements of an intentional relation in R.ST correspond to elements in the relations among intentions in Clk,S. all, one span is contributed with the intention of affecting the purpose of another span. In the original RST with only a. single relation between spans, the direction of the relation satellite to nucleus) always represented the direction of effect. simultaneous intentional and informational relations, nuclearity is an aspect of intentional relations only. The direction of an intentional relation in RST corresponds to dominance in GkS. That is, the satellite span, S, affects the purpose of the nucleus span, N, only if the intention that S realizes is dominated by the intention that S and N (and possibly others) realize together. Second of all, in R,ST, one span is intended to affect another in one of several ways. For example, satellite span, S, may be intended to affect a, hearer&apos;s belief in the nucleus span, N, (the relation); or S may be intended to affect a hearer&apos;s desire to perform the action indicated by N Correspondingly in GkS, intentions of various kinds may dominate other intentions. Roughly speaking, intentions realized by speaking are to either affect a hearer&apos;s or her actions. can occur only when the dominating intention to affect another&apos;s belief. Similarly, an RST can occur only when the intention to affect another&apos;s action. Thus the different kinds of intentional effects in RST correspond to different kinds of dominating intentions in G&amp;S. However, RST makes more kinds of effects than G&amp;S, e.g., both EVIDENCE and ways of beliefs and both ways affecting actions. Now we turn to the status of informational relations in the two theories. In RST, a single informational relation is assigned between spans of text. As a, result, RST informational relations concern the sorts of entities denoted by entire spans, such as situations and events. If we adopt the view of Moore and Pollack, recognizing that informational and intentional relations occur simultaneously, the informational relations are simplified. As noted above, nuclearity, which was an element of the unique RST relation between spans N and 5, is now an element, of the intentional relation and is independent of the informational relation. That is, informational relations no longer the link between situations expressed by two spans :itid the dominance of speaker 95 intentions realized by those spans. In fact, without this conflation, it is unclear whether the semantic relations between situations and events is in principle different from semantic links between other kinds of entities. Is the informational relation between two spans of text necessarily a relation between the entire spans? Or, is it possible that the informational relation is a series of links between various expressions contained in the spans? Examples of these links between smaller constituents are would are coreference and a. causal link between expressions such as &amp;quot;run a red light&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;the ticket.&amp;quot; GkS stresses that intentions of the speaker are the primary source of discourse structure. Domain knowledge plays a role in recognizing the intentional structure, but it is doubtful whether any special distinction would be made between knowledge about events and situations and knowledge about other kinds of domain entities. In comparing the status of intentional and infbrinational discourse relations in both RST and GkS, at least two issues were specified whose resolution is currently presumed by both theories in isolation. First, what types of dominance are distinguished by the theory— just dominance, dominance by belief-affecting intention versus dominance by action-affecting intention, or the full range of RST intentional relations? Second, do semantic links between whole spans of text play a. role in the theory, or do semantic relations between all sorts of entities have the same status? Both these questions can be answered separately depending on whether they are meant as a question about linguistic theory or about its application to language processing. Space precludes a discussion of textual discourse relations as yell a,s questions about how the three kinds of relations interact. Further, proposals from linguists (Schiffrin 1987; Redeker 1992) must be integrated into the synthesis. We conclude by sketching a discourse analysis study which begins to address the first question cited above, one which we plan to do. Using a broad range of text types, we select as tokens the pairs of spans that are related by lexical markers of discourse relations such as &amp;quot;so,&amp;quot; &amp;quot;because&amp;quot; and &amp;quot;therefore.&amp;quot; For each token, we code the informational and intentional relations that co-occur with it. As emphasized by Moore and Paris (1992), there is not a one-to-one mapping between intentional and informational relations. Though not completely independent, the possibilities for informational relations given the occurrence of a particular intentional relation are many, and vice versa. By investigating the range of combinations of informational and intentional relations which occur with a lexical marker, we can identify the minimal description of the marker in tennis of discourse relations. That is, we can see whether a. marker correlates highly with a particular disconrse relation or combination of informational and intentional relations. Such a. study will produce results that are useful for computational models of both natural language understanding and generation. If a certain marker correlates highly with certain discourse relations, the understander can form hypotheses about the discourse relations that are present when it encounters a. marker. Similarly, if a generator must express two utterances connected by a. certain combination of relations, it can use the information about the correlation between markers and combinations of discourse relations to choose the most appropriate marker. In addition, this study will allow its to determine whether the distinction among types of dominance plays a. role in accounting for the distribution of markers. If the study confirms the relevance of this distinction, then dominance types have a. role to play in a. linguistic theory of discourse coherence. If the study does not confirm the distinction, a. crucial theoretical question is whether there is any direct formal linguistic pattern other than these markers that makes essential use of dominance types in its description. Should further research fail to identify such a pattern, then the status of dominance types in linguistic theory is called into question. However, even if it turns out that dominance types are not formally marked by language, it remains an open question whether their application to computer generation and understanding will be useful.</abstract>
<note confidence="0.955230041666667">96 References [1] Grosz, B., 1978. Focusing in Dialog, Tinlap-2: Theoretical Issues in Natural Language Processing 7: 96-103. New York: Association for Computing Machinery and Association of Computational Linguistics. [2] Grosz, B. J. and Sidner, C. L., 1986. Attention, intention, and the structure of discourse. Linguistics [3] Hovy, E. and E. Maier, 1992. Parsimonious or Profligate: How Many and Which Discourse Structure Relations. ms. Submitted for publication. [4] Mann, W. C. and Thompson, S. A., 1988. Rhetorical Structure Theory: Towards a functional of text organization. [5] Moore, J. D. and Pollack, M. E., 1992. A problem for RST: The need for multi-level discourse Linguistics [6] Moore, J. D. and Paris, C. L., 1992. Planning Text For Advisory Dialogues: Capturing Intentional and Rhetorical Information. University of Pittsburgh, Department of Computer Science Report Number 92-22. for [7] Moser, M., 1992. Analysis of conversational arguments. Presentation to Washington Linguistics Society, Washington, DC, November 12. Working paper. [8] Redeker, G., 1992. Coherence and Structure in Text and Discourse. ins. Under review. Redeker, G., 1990. Ideational and Pragmatic Markers of Discourse Structure. of 367-81. [10] Sanders, T. J. M., W. P. M. S. Spooren and L. G. M. Noordman, 1992. Towards a Taxonomy Coherence Relations. Processes 1-35. Schiffrin, D., 1987. Markers. Cambridge .University Press.</note>
<intro confidence="0.348844">97</intro>
</variant>
</algorithm>
<algorithm name="ParsCit" version="110505">
<citationList>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B Grosz</author>
</authors>
<title>Focusing in Dialog, Tinlap-2: Theoretical Issues in</title>
<date>1978</date>
<journal>Natural Language Processing</journal>
<volume>7</volume>
<pages>96--103</pages>
<publisher>Association for</publisher>
<location>New York:</location>
<marker>[1]</marker>
<rawString>Grosz, B., 1978. Focusing in Dialog, Tinlap-2: Theoretical Issues in Natural Language Processing 7: 96-103. New York: Association for Computing Machinery and Association of Computational Linguistics.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>B J Grosz</author>
<author>C L Sidner</author>
</authors>
<title>Attention, intention, and the structure of discourse.</title>
<date>1986</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics</journal>
<pages>12--3</pages>
<marker>[2]</marker>
<rawString>Grosz, B. J. and Sidner, C. L., 1986. Attention, intention, and the structure of discourse. Computational Linguistics 12(3):175-204.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>E Hovy</author>
<author>E Maier</author>
</authors>
<title>Parsimonious or Profligate: How Many and Which Discourse Structure Relations.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<note>ms. Submitted for publication.</note>
<marker>[3]</marker>
<rawString>Hovy, E. and E. Maier, 1992. Parsimonious or Profligate: How Many and Which Discourse Structure Relations. ms. Submitted for publication.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>W C Mann</author>
<author>S A Thompson</author>
</authors>
<title>Rhetorical Structure Theory: Towards a functional theory of text organization.</title>
<date>1988</date>
<journal>TEXT</journal>
<pages>8--3</pages>
<marker>[4]</marker>
<rawString>Mann, W. C. and Thompson, S. A., 1988. Rhetorical Structure Theory: Towards a functional theory of text organization. TEXT 8(3):243-281.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J D Moore</author>
<author>M E Pollack</author>
</authors>
<title>A problem for RST: The need for multi-level discourse analysis.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<journal>Computational Linguistics</journal>
<volume>18</volume>
<issue>4</issue>
<marker>[5]</marker>
<rawString>Moore, J. D. and Pollack, M. E., 1992. A problem for RST: The need for multi-level discourse analysis. Computational Linguistics 18(4).</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>J D Moore</author>
<author>C L Paris</author>
</authors>
<title>Planning Text For Advisory Dialogues: Capturing Intentional and Rhetorical Information.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<tech>Technical Report Number 92-22.</tech>
<institution>University of Pittsburgh, Department of Computer Science</institution>
<note>Submitted for publication.</note>
<marker>[6]</marker>
<rawString>Moore, J. D. and Paris, C. L., 1992. Planning Text For Advisory Dialogues: Capturing Intentional and Rhetorical Information. University of Pittsburgh, Department of Computer Science Technical Report Number 92-22. Submitted for publication.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>M Moser</author>
</authors>
<title>Analysis of conversational arguments. Presentation to Washington Linguistics Society,</title>
<date>1992</date>
<location>Washington, DC,</location>
<note>Working paper.</note>
<marker>[7]</marker>
<rawString>Moser, M., 1992. Analysis of conversational arguments. Presentation to Washington Linguistics Society, Washington, DC, November 12. Working paper.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G Redeker</author>
</authors>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>Coherence and Structure in Text and Discourse. ins. Under review.</booktitle>
<marker>[8]</marker>
<rawString>Redeker, G., 1992. Coherence and Structure in Text and Discourse. ins. Under review.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>G Redeker</author>
</authors>
<title>Ideational and Pragmatic Markers of Discourse Structure.</title>
<date>1990</date>
<journal>Journal of Pragmatics</journal>
<volume>14</volume>
<pages>367--81</pages>
<marker>[9]</marker>
<rawString>Redeker, G., 1990. Ideational and Pragmatic Markers of Discourse Structure. Journal of Pragmatics 14: 367-81.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>T J M Sanders</author>
<author>W P M S Spooren</author>
<author>L G M Noordman</author>
</authors>
<title>Towards a Taxonomy of Coherence Relations.</title>
<date>1992</date>
<booktitle>Discourse Processes</booktitle>
<volume>15</volume>
<pages>1--35</pages>
<marker>[10]</marker>
<rawString>Sanders, T. J. M., W. P. M. S. Spooren and L. G. M. Noordman, 1992. Towards a Taxonomy of Coherence Relations. Discourse Processes 15: 1-35.</rawString>
</citation>
<citation valid="true">
<authors>
<author>D Schiffrin</author>
</authors>
<title>Discourse Markers. Cambridge:</title>
<date>1987</date>
<publisher>Cambridge .University Press.</publisher>
<marker>[11]</marker>
<rawString>Schiffrin, D., 1987. Discourse Markers. Cambridge: Cambridge .University Press.</rawString>
</citation>
</citationList>
</algorithm>
</algorithms>